Guide to the Paul Joseph Bass Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Paul Joseph Bass papers
1966-2004
MS 1826
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4
The papers consist of topical files and clippings relating to the career of Paul Bass as a journalist primarily covering affairs in New Haven and Connecticut. The collection includes topical files relating to the American Independent Movement, the New Haven Independent, Richard C. Lee, former New Haven Police chief, Nicholas Pastore, and other topics. It also includes clippings of articles by both Paul and Carole Bass, and dates back to Paul Bass' time as a student at the Horace Mann School.
Bass, Paul, 1960-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Paul Bass, 2003.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I. Topical Files, 1966-1999. II. Writings, 1977-2004.
Biographical / Historical
Paul Joseph Bass was born in 1960. He grew up in White Plains, New York, and attended the Horace Mann School in the Bronx, New York. At Horace Mann, he wrote for a variety of student publications and also contributed to Westchester County newspapers, where he would frequently work during summers. As a student at Yale College, Bass continued to participate in journalism primarily as a writer for the Yale Daily News and also as a contributor to other newspapers. After graduation in 1982, Bass became a free-lance journalist, with his writings appearing in such newspapers as the New Haven Advocate, New York Times, In These Times, and many others. In 1986, Bass, his wife, Carole, and another couple founded a weekly newspaper called the New Haven Independent. In 1989, he joined the staff of the New Haven Advocate. He has won numerous awards and is known for reporting on social, political, and cultural issues in New Haven and around the world.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of topical files and clippings relating to the career of Paul Bass as a journalist primarily covering affairs in New Haven and Connecticut. The collection includes topical files relating to the American Independent Movement, the, Richard C. Lee, former New Haven Police chief, Nicholas Pastore, and other topics. It also includes clippings of articles by both Paul and Carole Bass, and dates back to Paul Bass' time as a student at the Horace Mann School.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
New Haven advocate; New Haven independent; Journalists -- Connecticut; New Haven (Conn.); Bass, Carole; Bass, Paul, 1960-; Lee, Richard C. (Richard Charles), 1916-2003; Pastore, Nicholas; American Independent Movement (Conn.)
- Topical Files, 1966-1999, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Arranged alphabetically, the series includes research materials used by Paul and Carole Bass. It also includes administrative files relating to the New Haven Independent, a weekly independent newspaper with an emphasis on investigative journalism, published in the late 1980s. Materials related to the American Independent Movement consist of FBI files obtained by Paul Bass through a Freedom Of Information Act request, and they document the activities of a leftist radical group functioning in New Haven during 1960s.
  - American Independent Movement, 1966-1971 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 12)
  - Book proposal: The City of Good Intentions, 1998-1999, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Bass, Carole [resume], undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Cooperative News Service
    - General, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Clippings, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 16 - 18)
  - Downey, Morton, Jr. [correspondence, notes, photographs, and articles relating to scuffle with Bass], 1988 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - International Society of Newspaper Editors Golden Quill Award [Bass a finalist], 1991 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Lee, Dick [notes and interviews], Circa 1986-Circa 1998 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - New Haven Independent
    - Administrative memoranda and policies, 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Administrative memoranda and policies circulation, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Advertisement flyers, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Board of directors and shareholders list, 1987-1988, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Business Plan, [1985] (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - City of New Haven board of aldermen resolution, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Consultants [reports, correspondence, and other material], 1986-1989 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence, 1985-1989, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Clippings relating to New Haven Independent, 1986-1989 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Dow, John, Jr. [libel suit], 1987 (Box 3, Folder 32 - 35)
    - Editorial memoranda and policy, Circa 1986 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Financial and legal documents, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 37 - 38)
    - Meeting minutes, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Readers survey, undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Reading packet with articles relating to New Haven Independent: Paul Bass guest lecturer, 1986-1989, undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Pastore, Nicholas
    - Book proposals, undated (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Clippings, 1990-1994, undated (Box 4, Folder 43 - 48)
    - Interviews, 1993 Sep, undated (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Legal documents and related, 1993, undated (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, publication, and other material, 1992-1994 (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - New Haven Needle Exchange Program, 1992-1994 (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - Notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 53)
- Writings, 1977-2004, Series II
  Arranged chronologically, the series consists of clippings of Paul Bass articles from the Horace Mann Record, Reporter Dispatch (White Plains, New York), Yale Daily News, New Haven Register, Hartford Courant, New York Times, Fair Haven News, In These Times, New Haven Independent, and New Haven Advocate. The series also contains clippings of Carole Bass articles from many of the same publications. The series ranges from when Paul Bass was a high school student at Horace Mann in New York to his time as an associate editor of the New Haven Advocate.
  The series reflects the careers of Paul and Carole Bass as investigative journalists primarily working in New Haven, Connecticut, and therefore documents most of the major news stories in the city from the early 1980s through the mid-2000s.
  - 1977 fall-1978 spring [ Horace Mann Record and other Horace Mann and other Horace Mann newspapers] (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - 1977 Sep-1978 May [ Reporter Dispatch ] (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - 1978 summer (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - 1978 Sep-1979 May [ Reporter Dispatch ] (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - 1978 Sep-1979 May [ Yale Daily News ] (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - 1979 summer (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - 1979 fall-1980 spring [ Yale Daily News ] (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - 1980 summer-1980 fall (Box 5, Folder 8 - 9)
  - 1980 fall-1981 spring [Smith (later Bass), Carole: Yale Daily News ] (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - 1981 [Smith (later Bass), Carole: Today ] (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - 1981-1982 winter/spring (Box 5, Folder 12 - 15)
  - 1982 fall-1983 summer (Box 6, Folder 16 - 18)
  - 1983-1984 [Bass, Paul and/or Carole] (Box 6, Folder 19 - 22)
  - 1985 [Bass, Paul and Carole: freelance writings] (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - 1986 [Bass, Paul and Carole] (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - 1987-1989 [Bass, Carole: New Haven Independent ] (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - 1989-1990 [ New Haven Advocate ] (Box 7, Folder 26 - 28)
  - 1990 [Bass, Carole, editor: Fair Haven News ] (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - 1991-1995 [ New Haven Advocate ] (Box 7, Folder 30 - 38)
  - 1995-1998 [ New Haven Advocate ] (Box 8, Folder 39 - 44)
  - 1998-2004 [ New Haven Advocate ] (Box 9, Folder 45 - 56)
  - Miscellaneous dates [freelance writings] (Box 9, Folder 57)
  - Miscellaneous dates [Bass, Paul and Carole] (Box 9, Folder 58)